<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Duncan Cai</title>
    <description>aspiring software engineer</description>
    <link>http://femmebot.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://femmebot.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2-dimensional strip packing problem (2DSPP), we are given a set of rectangles of height and width greater than 0 and less than or equal to 1, and we wish to pack them in a container (or strip) of width 1 and infinite height. We want the packing to have the smallest height possible. The problem is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hardness&quot;&gt;NP-hard&lt;/a&gt; meaning it is very difficult to find the arrangement of rectangles which gives us the smallest height. When we can’t find the exact solution easily, we try to design &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approximation_algorithm&quot;&gt;approximation algorithms&lt;/a&gt; which give solutions which are not optimal, but within a factor of the optimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high multiplicity strip packing problem is a type of 2DSPP where we are given a set of different types of rectangles (rectangles with different widths and heights), but we want to pack a certain number of each of these rectangles. Therefore, many of the rectangles that we wish to pack are duplicates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my undergraduate thesis, I was looking to improve upon an algorithm for solving the high multiplicity strip packing problem in the case where there are only four rectangle types.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I wrote a program that visualizes solutions for the rectangle packing problem to give me ideas for solving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-idea&quot;&gt;General Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to solve the strip packing problem is by first solving the &lt;strong&gt;fractional strip packing problem&lt;/strong&gt;. In the fractional version of the problem, we are allowed to cheat by cutting rectangles in pieces and packing these fractional pieces instead. It turns out that the fractional strip packing problem is much easier to solve than the strip packing problem, and we can find an optimal solution quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;image centered&quot;&gt;

&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;An example of a fractional packing. Notice how some rectangles are not whole.

&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/packing.png&quot; alt=&quot;An example of a fractional packing. Notice how some rectangles are not whole.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have an optimal solution for the fractional strip packing problem, we must convert the fractional packing into an integral packing. This means we need to combine the fractional pieces into whole rectangles such that there no fractional pieces left over. This will always increase the height of the packing since we need more space to fit whole rectangles than fractional rectangles. This is the hard part. How do we combine the fractional parts into whole rectangles without increasing the height of the packing by too much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fractional solution uses space as efficiently as possible, the optimal solution cannot have a lower height. This is a very useful property since it means that the height of the fractional solution acts as a lower bound for the height of the optimal solution–whatever the optimal is.  For example, if we increase the height of the fractional solution by K when we convert it into an integral solution then our resulting solution cannot be greater than the height of the optimal solution plus K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Price’s paper, he found a way to pack K rectangle types with a height increase of K - 1. For four rectangle types, this gives us a height increase of 3. The aim of my thesis is to try to pack four rectangles with a height increase of less than 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, it might not be obvious how solving the 2DSPP is useful. Here is an interesting application of the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have a rectangular slab of material, which could be cloth, wood, glass etc. You want to cut various pieces out of it for building furniture, making cloth etc., but you want to minimize the amount of material that is wasted when you do this. The slab of material in this case corresponds to the strip in 2DSPP, and the pieces that we need to cut out from the material correspond to the rectangles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology&quot;&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program was written in Javascript and uses HTML5 Canvas to draw the shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ir.lib.uwo.ca/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3369&amp;amp;context=etd&quot;&gt;High Multiplicity Strip Packing&lt;/a&gt; by Devon Price &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://femmebot.github.io/Thesis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://femmebot.github.io/Thesis/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bin Packing</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bin packing web application intended to demonstrate the effectiveness of bin packing approximation algorithms. In the classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bin_packing_problem&quot;&gt;bin packing problem&lt;/a&gt;, we want to pack a set of items of various weights into bins of equal size by using the least number of bins. It is very difficult to find the exact solution to this problem because it belongs to the set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hardness&quot;&gt;NP-hard&lt;/a&gt; problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, there are a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approximation_algorithm&quot;&gt;approximation algorithms&lt;/a&gt; that will not find the optimal solution but will find a solution that is close to the optimal solution. In my web application, I explore the performance of two different algorithms named &lt;strong&gt;first fit&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;first fit descending&lt;/strong&gt; through a simple game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose is to show how well approximation algorithms–which do not find the exact solution–perform in practice. I was surprised by how difficult it is for to beat the computer’s “dumb” approach to solving the problem (described below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-fit&quot;&gt;First Fit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first fit algorithm is the simplest algorithm that one can think of for solving the bin packing problem. For each item, we put it in the first bin that fits. If there are no bins where this item fits, we open a new bin and we put the item there. It can be shown that this algorithm produces a solution that is at most two times the optimal solution. That means if the optimal solution uses X bins then this solution uses at most 2X bins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;image centered&quot;&gt;

&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Illustration of first fit bin packing
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vUxhAmfXs2o&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/vUxhAmfXs2o/hqdefault.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of first fit bin packing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-fit-descending&quot;&gt;First Fit Descending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first fit descending algorithm is an improvement upon the first fit algorithm. We first sort our items in decreasing order and then we pack them in the same way that we pack them in first fit. It can be shown that this algorthm produces a solution that is at most one-and-a-half (3/2) times the optimal solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this simple game, the player is a worker in a factory that is presumably in the business of packing boxes. Blue squares representing items of various sizes are generated to the left, with each square containing a number that indicates the weight of each box. The player’s objective is to pack these items into each bin using the least amount of bins. The computer will run first fit and first fit descending described above to solve the problems. The player’s aim is to solve the problem using less bins than the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the task of beating the computer simpler, the computer will take the worst solution between the ones given by first fit and first fit descending. The reason is that although first fit descending seems to be a better algorithm, it sometimes finds a worse solution than first fit in practice. This is also to make it less likely that the computer finds the optimal solution, in which case the user cannot do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology&quot;&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web application was coded mainly in Javascript. I used the libraries &lt;a href=&quot;https://jqueryui.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery UI&lt;/a&gt; for the drag/drop functionality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/react/&quot;&gt;React.js&lt;/a&gt; for updating the user interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://femmebot.github.io/Bin-Packing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://femmebot.github.io/Bin-Packing/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Transposer</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singers often have to change the key of their song so that the notes are within their vocal range. As someone who sometimes gives singing a try, I found myself going through the painstaking process of transposing chords by hand. To save myself some time, I wrote this program to transpose chords automatically for me. I did find some chord transposers online at the time, but I wasn’t satisfied with their performance. For example, they would often give the wrong form of a chord. For example, the chord &lt;strong&gt;Bb&lt;/strong&gt; would be given as &lt;strong&gt;A#&lt;/strong&gt;. They are the same chord&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but &lt;strong&gt;A#&lt;/strong&gt; is almost never seen and would be incorrect in most key signatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This web application contains a combination of several features that distinguish it from existing chord transposition software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chord-detection&quot;&gt;Chord Detection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given a bunch of lyrics containing both chords and lyrics, it can tell with reasonably high accuracy which text is a chord and which text are lyrics. It will then transpose only the chords, leaving the lyrics intact. It can identify and transpose a variety of chords including chords with suffixes such as &lt;strong&gt;Ab7&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Asus4&lt;/strong&gt; or chords with a bass note such as &lt;strong&gt;F/G&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;multiple-transposition-options&quot;&gt;Multiple Transposition Options&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user can choose to either transpose to a target key signature or transpose up/down a certain number of semitones. If the user chooses the latter option, the transposer will need to know the current key signature from the user. If the user does not provide the current key signature, then the transposer will naively infer the current key signature from the first chord. In the majority of cases, the first chord identifies the key signature, which saves users the trouble of having to state it for the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;knows-about-key-signatures&quot;&gt;Knows About Key Signatures&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transposer understands which chords are valid in the target key signature and will only output those chords. For example, if we are transposing to &lt;strong&gt;Bb&lt;/strong&gt; major, the chord transposer will not output &lt;strong&gt;A#&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;E#&lt;/strong&gt;, as these are not valid chords in &lt;strong&gt;Bb&lt;/strong&gt; major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology&quot;&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transposer library is written in Javascript and uses HTML/CSS for the user interface. To recognize chords, it uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://xregexp.com/&quot;&gt;XRegExp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expression&quot;&gt;regular expression&lt;/a&gt; javascript library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;They are called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enharmonic&quot;&gt;enharmonic equivalents&lt;/a&gt; since they are different notations for the same pitch. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://femmebot.github.io/Transposer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://femmebot.github.io/Transposer/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flood It</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the game Flood It, there is a grid of coloured squares and the user’s objective is to fill the entire grid with one colour. Each turn, the user can “flood” every cell connected to the top left corner of the grid with a single colour. All cells connected to the top left corner are changed to the designated colour. For two cells to be connected, they must have the same colour and be adjacent vertically or horizontally. The objective of the user is to flood the entire grid in the least number of turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;image centered&quot;&gt;

&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;Image of a Flood It board

&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/FloodItBoard.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Image of a Flood It board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving a game of Flood It belongs to the set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hardness&quot;&gt;NP-hard&lt;/a&gt; problems meaning it is very difficult to find an exact solution.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One simple algorithm to find an approximate solution is to choose the colour that will flood the largest area at each step. This algorithm is known as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greedy_algorithm&quot;&gt;greedy algorithm&lt;/a&gt; since it takes the locally optimal–but not necessarily globally optimal–action at each step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this game–other than having fun, of course–is to explore how the greedy algorithm performs in practice since it is not easy to analyze its performance. In my experience, it is pretty difficult to find a solution better than the optimal one produced by the computer. This might suggest that the greedy algorithm performs quite well on randomly generated puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the game, the computer solves the puzzle by employing the greedy algorithm mentioned above. The objective of the user is to try to beat the solution using fewer turns than the computer. The number of turns that the user used compared to the computer is displayed at the top as X/Y where X and Y are the number of turns used by the player and computer, respectively. The user can also ask the computer to solve the puzzle step-by-step using greedy algorithm by clicking the “Solve For Me” button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;algorithms&quot;&gt;Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;simple-cycling&quot;&gt;Simple Cycling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest algorithm for solving Flood It is to cycle through all of the colours until the board is filled. This will always solve the problem since at each turn, there must be a colour that gets us closer to the solution. This algorithm gives us a solution that is at most C times the optimal number of turns where C is the number of colours available.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Why is this true? Since each step of the optimal solution chooses some colour, if we try all of them we use up C turns for each turn that the optimal solution uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;greedy&quot;&gt;Greedy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the simple cycling algorithm, there is no limit to how many turns the greedy algorithm uses compared to the optimum. The greedy algorithm is the following: at each turn, we choose the colour that gives us the most “territory”. Although intuitively this seems like a good strategy, this may give us something far from the best solution. Consider the following puzzle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;image centered&quot;&gt;

&lt;caption align=&quot;bottom&quot;&gt;A puzzle for which the greedy algorithm performs badly
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://kunigami.wordpress.com/2012/09/16/flood-it-an-exact-approach/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://kunigami.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/flood-it-bad.png&quot; alt=&quot;A puzzle for which the greedy algorithm performs badly&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal solution takes three turns, which is the best we can possibly get. The solution is to flood the board in the following sequence: blue, red, then orange. Notice that the greedy algorithm will choose red first as it increases our territory the most. Then, it will choose orange then red then orange and so on. It will choose blue last. This is much worse than the optimal solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested to see if it’s easy for a user to beat a solution produced by the greedy algorithm even though it has been shown that it performs badly in some cases. Try it yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology&quot;&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is written in Javascript/&lt;a href=&quot;https://jquery.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; and HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1001.4420&quot;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt; that shows that Flood-It is NP-hard for boards of height &amp;gt;= 3. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kunigami.wordpress.com/2012/09/16/flood-it-an-exact-approach/&quot;&gt;Blog post&lt;/a&gt; that shows that the simple cycling algorithm gives an approximation ratio of C, the number of colours. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://femmebot.github.io/Flood-It/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://femmebot.github.io/Flood-It/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>